<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book SYSTEM "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/5.0b5/dtd/docbook.dtd" [
<!ENTITY code3 "file:///Users/Shared/Developer/Java/JHotDraw/current/git/jhotdraw/jhotdraw8/src/main/java/org/jhotdraw8/samples/mini/ConnectingFiguresSample.java" >
]>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:lang="en"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xml:id="eg.lineConnectionFigures">
    <title>Connecting two figures with a line</title>
    
    <para>A LineConnectionFigure can be used to connect two figures with a line.
        The line will stick to the two figures when the user moves or resizes the connected figures.</para>

    <para>The listing <xref  linkend="listing.ConnectingFiguresSample"/>  shows how to correctly set up a line connection figure.</para>

    <example xml:id="listing.ConnectingFiguresSample">
        <title>ConnectingFiguresSample</title>
        <programlisting language="java" linenumbering="numbered" startinglinenumber="1"><xi:include  href="&code3;"  parse="text"  /></programlisting>
    </example>
    
    <para>The example program performs the following steps:</para>
    <orderedlist>
  <listitem >
    <para>Create two rectangle figures and a line connection figure.</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>Connect the line connection figure to the rectangle figures using chop rectangle connectors. 
         The connectors implement the strategy for computing the connection locations.
          Instead of specifying the connectors by ourselves, we could request them
         from the rectangle figures. Depending on the coordinates and connection figure that we
        provide, we may get a different kind of connector or none at all.</para>
        <programlisting language="java">c.setStartConnection(a, a.findConnector(110,90, c));
c.setEndConnection(b, b.findConnector(310,240, c));  </programlisting>
  </listitem>
  <listitem >
    <para>Layout the line connection figure, so that it computes its start and end locations.
         
         The layout of the line connection figure depends on the layout of the rectangle figures.
         Each time you change the layout of one of the rectangle figures, you have to call
         layout on the connection figure. Figures do not automatically update their layout
         due to performance reasons. A DrawingModel can be used to automate this.</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem  >
    <para>Create a drawing and add a layer to it.
        Then add the figures to the layer.</para>
  </listitem>
</orderedlist>

</section>
