<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:lang="en" xml:id="design.MasterDetailsInspectorLayout">
  <title>Master-Details-Inspector Layout</title>

  <para>The master-details-inspector layout is a layout that consists of the following three panes:</para>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>The master pane in the left area of the window</para>
      <para>A master pane is a control that displays a collection of objects
        from which one can be selected.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>The details pane in the center area of the window</para>
      <para>A details pane is a control that displays the selected object from the master pane.
        The object can be structured from which one or multiple elements can be selected.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>The inspector pane in the right area of the window</para>
      <para>An inspector pane is a control that displays properties of the selected element
        in the details pane.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para>The master-details-inspector layout is used by many applications, and thus is well known
    and understood by most users.
  </para>

  <para>We can use the following design to implement this layout with JavaFX:</para>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>For each component (master pane, detail pane, inspector pane) we create a FXML
        file for the layout, and a JavaFX controller class: MasterPaneController,
        DetailsPaneController, InspectorPaneController.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>The MasterPaneController has a JavaFX ObservableList for the collection
        that it displays, and a JavaFX Property for the selected object
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>The DetailsPaneController has a JavaFX Property for the object that it displays
        and a JavaFX ObservableList for the selection of sub-objects.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>The InspectorPaneController has a JavaFX property for the selection of objects
        for which it can display properties.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>We can bind the properties of the panes with JavaFX bindings.</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>


  <para>This layout can be altered in various ways:</para>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>The master pane can be omitted, which leaves us with a details-inspector layout.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>The inspector pane can be omitted, which leaves us with a master-details layout.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>the master pane can support multiple selection, which turns the object that is
        displayed in the details pane into a collection.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>The inspector pane can only show the properties of the main object in the details
        pane instead from the selected sub-objects.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>The inspector pane can show properties of the details pane itself.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>The window can contain more than one inspector pane.</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

</section>
